Did you ever wonder if certain foods
have a direct effect on your health?
Well, I’m here to
solve that mystery
since you are
the foods you eat.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at the effect of
maternal diets on infant health.
Did you know that you can
treat the cause of infant reflux
with maternal cow’s
milk elimination?
Here’s our first story.
There has been a longstanding problem
among zookeepers of the gorilla.
Latin name: Gorilla, gorilla gorilla.
The problem is that they were
throwing up all the time.
We’ve never seen wild gorillas barfing,
but it had unfortunately been
accepted as routine by many zoos.
What were they feeding them?
Well, you know they’re
big strong animals,
so they made sure to
feed them lots of protein,
you know, cottage cheese,
meat, eggs, milk.;
until a zoo in Germany
got this radical idea
to try giving them their natural diet.
And the change following the
alterations to the diet was astonishing.
I mean before, the poor silverback
was regurgitating and vomiting
during most of the day.
But by the third day eating what
they were supposed to eat,
he and the rest were
all miraculously cured.
Even just removing milk from
captive gorilla diets
led to significant improvement.
Cow’s milk was historically
considered an essential item
in the captive gorilla diet,
but they showed that removal
of milk from the captive gorilla diet
may reduce such undesirable behaviors
and may be a step toward better
approximating their natural diet.
I mean giving an animal
milk after weaning?
Giving an adult animal milk?
Milk is for babies!
And then giving milk from
a bovine to a primate?
What were these crazy
zookeepers thinking?
Doesn’t make any sense!
Reminds me of this landmark study.
Eighty-one children presenting with
reflux, gastroesophageal reflux disease,
so they were given drugs,
and two thirds got better,
but 27 kids still did not.
So, they tried eliminating cow’s milk
from their diets, and within
one month, all 27 were cured.
Symptoms of acid regurgitation,
heartburn, or both, occur
at least once a week in 10–20 percent
of adults in the western world.
And in about up to 25
percent of all infants.
Now it’s normal for babies
to spit up occasionally—
that’s not what we’re talking about.
It can actually get quite serious.
Up to a quarter of infants present
with regurgitation severe enough
for parents to seek medical help,
and it may just be that they’re
sensitive to cow’s milk.
The symptoms of cow’s milk protein
allergy overlap or may coexist
or complicate GERD or reflux.
Even if there’s no formal
dairy allergy per se,
there appears to be some kind
of cow’s milk ‘hypersensitivity’
among many infants and
children with severe reflux.
There are all sorts of
invasive tests you can do,
like stick pH probes down
the poor baby’s throat,
but probably the most practical test
in routine pediatric practice
is just a trial of a cow’s milk
protein elimination diet
for two to four weeks
in infants with reflux.
The gold standard is what’s called an
elimination and re-challenge protocol,
where you see full resolution of
symptoms via a strict elimination,
followed by recurrence of the symptoms
on reintroduction of cow’s milk protein.
And when you do that, take 200 or
so infants diagnosed with reflux
and then not only put them
on a cow’s milk-free diet,
but then do the challenge tests.
Eighty-five of the 204 infants with
reflux were actually suffering
from a cow’s milk allergy or at least
hypersensitivity or something.
What we think is happening is
that our immune system attacks
the bovine proteins as
understandably foreign,
triggering an inflammatory response,
which like irritates the nerves
lining your digestive tract,
and that results in abnormalities
in the rhythmic contractions
of the stomach, triggering
the regurgitation.
And we’re not just talking
about formula-fed infants.
Cow’s milk protein allergy can occur
in exclusively breastfed infants,
as intact cow’s milk proteins can
be secreted in breast milk.
If the mom drinks milk or eats
eggs it can get into her baby.
Cow’s milk protein and other foreign
proteins can pass into human breast milk.
So breast-fed infants with regurgitation
and vomiting may therefore benefit from
a trial of withdrawal of cow’s milk
and eggs from the maternal diet.
And indeed, that is now the
consensus recommendation of both
the North American and European
Society for Pediatric
Gastroenterology, Hepatology,
and Nutrition.
Anytime you see reflux, let’s
first try a therapeutic trial
of either a cow’s milk protein–free
formula or, for infants who are breastfed,
a maternal strict cow’s milk
protein elimination diet.
And so, then we can potentially
treat the cause without
using unnecessary medications,
and certainly before you start
considering performing
any anti-reflux surgery
on the poor kid.
In our next story,
we look at how cow’s milk proteins
can pass through breast milk—
which may explain why
maternal dairy-free diets
are so effective in
treating infant colic.
Colic affects up to 40%
of young infants,
characterized by prolonged periods
of inconsolable crying.
The condition is often
dismissed as trivial
by the medical profession,
but should be treated seriously.
It can contribute to
postpartum depression,
interfere with breastfeeding,
and even lead to the
death of the infant
at the hands of a parent
from shaken baby syndrome.
They’re not just crybabies.
Colic is pain.
The medical profession has
a scandalous history
not just denying pain
relief to infants,
but routinely performing
surgery on infants
with minimal or no
anesthesia into the 1980’s.
One famous case in 1985
was little Jeffrey Lawson,
who underwent open
heart surgery
fully awake and conscious.
They just gave him a drug to
paralyze him so he wouldn’t squirm,
but like a horror
movie he couldn’t move
but could feel everything.
This wasn’t some rogue surgeon,
torturing babies was standard
operating procedure in the 80’s.
Not the 1880’s, mind you,
the 1980’s.
The liaison between the
American Academy of Pediatrics
and the Society of Anesthesiologists
commented that the use
of paralyzing agents
was a standard and
time-honored technique.
The profession has a history
of infant pain denial.
They didn’t think
babies could feel pain.
Even today, most physicians
don’t use pain-killers
or even local anesthesia
for circumcisions, for example,
a procedure so traumatic
the babies show
stronger pain responses to
vaccinations even months later.
The pain of colic,
is thought to be caused
by gastrointestinal discomfort,
like intestinal cramping.
In my videos on irritable bowel
and relaxing the colon
before a colonoscopy
I explored the role
of peppermint oil
in reducing intestinal spasms,
so might it help with colic?
A few drops of a peppermint
leaf solution appeared
to cut the number of
colicky episodes in half,
and reduced daily crying from
three hours to two hours,
working just as well as the
leading over-the-counter drug
for colic called simethicone.
The problem is that simethicone
has been shown to have
no benefit for colic,
so saying peppermint
is as good as useless
isn’t exactly a ringing
endorsement.
And the American Academy of Pediatrics
warns about the use of
peppermint oil in infants.
One study found an herbal
tea preparation to be helpful,
but parents have been
cautioned not to use them,
not only because tea may interfere
with breastfeeding continuity,
but the lack of adequate
industry regulation.
For example, star anise tea
is commonly used for colic.
Chinese star anise is regarded
as safe and nontoxic,
but Japanese star
anise is poisonous.
They look identical,
but Japanese star anise
contains a potent neurotoxin,
and it’s been found contaminating
star anise tea in the U.S.,
and so we shouldn’t
give it to kids.
There’s even a
report of toxicity
from a supposed homeopathic
dose of belladonna,
also known as
deadly nightshade,
that evidently wasn’t homeopathic
enough, and then another.
Just because it’s homeopathic doesn’t
necessarily mean it’s safe.
It’s no better when doctors
prescribe it though.
The drugs used for colic are
made from belladonna too.
The drugs may work,
but should not be used
because of their
serious side effects.
What about just good
old fashioned burping?
Burping after feeding is,
after all, commonly advised
by pediatricians, nurses
and parenting websites
to promote expulsion of gases that
accumulate during feeding
with the aim of decreasing
discomfort and crying episodes,
but scientific evidence for the
efficacy of burping is lacking,
until this 2014 randomized
controlled trial
for the prevention of colic
and regurgitation,
also known as spitting up,
in healthy infants.
So what did they find?
Useless for colic, and made
the regurgitation worse.
Burped babies spit up twice
as many times as unburped babies!
So what’s an
effective treatment?
The elimination of
cow’s milk protein,
thinking colic may be some
sort of allergic response.
Decades ago it was shown
that infants fed cow’s milk
developed antibody responses
to the bovine proteins,
which may explain why
colic can improve
after changing from a
cow’s milk formula
to either a hypoallergenic
hydrolyzed protein formula
or a soy-based formula.
Now, breast fed infants
have similar rates
of colic as formula
fed infants,
but that might be because breast
milk from milk drinking mothers
contains cow's milk proteins.
We know cow’s milk proteins
can pass through breast milk
and cause certain serious
allergic reactions,
but what about colic?
Based on studies of
formula fed infants,
colic was already a well-known
symptom of intolerance
to cow’s-milk protein
back in the 70’s,
so thinking colic in
breast-fed infants
may be caused by cow’s-milk
proteins transmitted
from mother to infant
via breast milk,
they tried a dairy-free diet
for breast-feeding mothers
whose infants had colic.
Of 19 infants, the colic
disappeared promptly from 13,
and in 12 of those 13
they were able to show
that they could bring
back the colic by
challenging the mothers
with a little dairy.
For example, baby boy
develops colic
that almost completely
disappears within a day
of mom eliminating cow’s milk,
and then promptly comes back
when mom went back on dairy.
The researches conclude that
the treatment for infantile colic
in breast-fed infants is a diet
free of cow’s milk for the mother,
a recommendation that
continues to this day.
Finally today,
we look at how spirulina
supplements with toxins
from blue-green algae raise
safety concerns for nursing mothers.
On his first day of life an infant
is hospitalized with seizures.
The researchers concluded that his
mother's daily spirulina use
starting in the 4th month of
pregnancy was likely to blame.
I've talked previously about
the liver and nerve toxins
present in many spirulina supplements,
but the supplement companies
swear up and down
that spirulina doesn't produce
these toxins and they may be right.
But if spirulina doesn't produce toxins,
how was it that toxins have
been repeatedly been found
in spirulina supplements?
It appears to be contamination of spirulina
with toxin-producing blue-green algae.
So for example if you look at the new U.S.
Pharmacopeia safety evaluation of spirulina,
they conclude that the available
evidence does not indicate
a serious risk or other
public health concern
when spirulina is properly
identified, formulated, and used.
Ah, but that's the catch!
You collect spirulina
in some open lake
and you have no idea what other
algae are going to crop up.
The researchers report
all sorts of adverse reactions
in people taking
spirulina products,
but they attribute these issues to
non-spirulina algae toxin contaminants
within spirulina supplements
known to be toxic to the liver
and cancer-causing.
So unless there's third-party
testing of each batch,
which no company could
presumably afford to do,
I continue to encourage people
to avoid spirulina products.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.